<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: browsers | ]]></title>
  <link href="/categories/browsers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-11T13:55:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walking, talking and ideas for web apps]]></title>
    <link href="/browsers/mobile/webapps/2015/02/11/walking-talking-and-ideas-for-web-apps.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-11T08:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/browsers/mobile/webapps/2015/02/11/walking-talking-and-ideas-for-web-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An issue came up in a recent team meeting: in Developer Relations, how do you 
remain a leading expert in the field? My answer: Create. Build. Tell a story 
about what you have learnt. It is <a href="https://medium.com/@romannurik/walk-then-talk-3b935bfe5484">a principle shared by Roman Nurik</a> 
which he called “Walk, then Talk”; I encourage you to read his post.</p>

<p>Our team, Chrome Developer Relations, are doing just this right now. We are 
building real-world apps that let us:</p>

<ul>
  <li>stretch our understanding of how to build modern web applications; </li>
  <li>push the capabilities of the web platform as they are developed; </li>
  <li>define new patterns for how to combine existing and bleeding edge platform 
features;</li>
  <li>create great stories that tell developers how they can also build similar 
quality applications using the same tools. </li>
</ul>

<p>If we can achieve this and socialize it well, it is my hope that we increase the 
minimum bar for what developers should deliver on the web and raise the 
expectation of user experience from users (I’ll talk more about this in another 
post, but I am using it to set the scene for this post.)</p>

<p>As a team we are lucky, we have a reasonable idea about the types of apps that 
we want to build and also the apps that we want to see on the web. But a lot of 
developers that I speak to struggle for ideas of what they can build.</p>

<p>I was catching up with Jake Archibald about how he came up with idea for 
<a href="https://jakearchibald.github.io/svgomg/">SVGOMG</a>  — SVGOMG is a great app for optimizing SVGs, it’s hard to tell that it is not a native app. It has a nice Material design, loads quickly, runs at 60fps, works 
across form-factors and has great use of touch gestures — and it came from the 
fact that people said SVGO was hard to use and needed a front end. A project was 
born!</p>

<p>He then used <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">npm</a>, found the <a href="https://github.com/svg/svgo">SVGO</a> and that gave 
him the impetus to create SVGOMG, a front-end client for a service library.</p>

<p>I think this is a brilliant idea! The promise of NodeJS is that it enables you 
to do full-stack development in one language. NodeJS and npm have built up a 
huge ecosystem (&gt; 120,000 packages) of JS libraries, tools and utilities, 
primarily focused on the server side of your application.</p>

<p>I’m going to ask you take a mental jump, because getting I am going to skip how 
to get NodeJS packages working in the browser, but it requires you to use 
<a href="http://browserify.org/">Browserify</a>, which to quote the Browserify site:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>browserify will recursively analyze all the require() calls in your app in 
order to build a bundle you can serve up to the browser in a single 
&lt;script&gt; tag.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Not every package will be browserify-erable, especially if it is a JS wrapper 
for an system level service (in which case Emscripten is an option), but the 
crux is, by using NPM and browserify we now have a huge repository of libraries 
that have done a huge amount of heavy lifting and are crying out for a 
beautiful, modern web app client.</p>

<p>What makes a modern web app? That comes in another post (Sorry).</p>

<p>I spent 20 minutes curating potential project ideas whilst casually browsing 
npm. I have also added them to the <a href="https://github.com/WebUtils/Platform/issues">WebUtils</a> 
project which is a great place to collaborate and discuss what should be built 
and how to build it.</p>

<h2 id="converters"><strong>Converters</strong></h2>

<p>Conversion tools are always a great source of app ideas.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Unit Convert: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/convert-units">https://www.npmjs.com/package/convert-units</a></li>
  <li>Currency Converter: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/currency">https://www.npmjs.com/package/currency</a></li>
  <li>Sprite SVG Images: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/spritemaker-svg">https://www.npmjs.com/package/spritemaker-svg</a></li>
  <li>WebCam 2 Gif: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/gif-encoder">https://www.npmjs.com/package/gif-encoder</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="calculators"><strong>Calculators</strong></h2>

<p>A simple search for 
“<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/browse/keyword/calculator">calculator</a>” reveals a huge 
plethora of utilities that you can build upon.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Loan Calculator:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/packages/financial-loan-calculator-engine">https://www.npmjs.com/packages/financial-loan-calculator-engine</a></li>
  <li>Roman Numerals:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/packages/deromanize">https://www.npmjs.com/packages/deromanize</a></li>
  <li>Student Loan Calculator:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/packages/uk-student-loan">https://www.npmjs.com/packages/uk-student-loan</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="calendars-and-dates"><strong>Calendars and Dates</strong></h2>

<p>It constantly vexes me that every calendar I see on the web is 1) terrible, 2) 
optimized for desktop 3) full of ads and rubbish I don’t need.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A Simple calendar: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/calendar">https://www.npmjs.com/package/calendar</a></li>
  <li>Days/Time until: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/timediff">https://www.npmjs.com/package/timediff</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="image-tools"><strong>Image tools</strong></h2>

<p>Who doesn’t want to manipulate images and why do we need native apps for actions 
we only perform a couple of times.</p>

<ul>
  <li>RGB Analysis:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/rgbanalyse">https://www.npmjs.com/package/rgbanalyse</a></li>
  <li>Object detector:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/pixfinder">https://www.npmjs.com/package/pixfinder</a></li>
  <li>Exif reader: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/exif">https://www.npmjs.com/package/exif</a></li>
  <li>Quick image cropper:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/scrissors">https://www.npmjs.com/package/scrissors</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="qr-codes"><strong>QR Codes</strong></h2>

<p>Every so often, you need to scan a QR code. Why do you need a native app for 
something you only use once in a blue moon.</p>

<ul>
  <li>QR Code generator:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/qrcode">https://www.npmjs.com/package/qrcode</a></li>
  <li>QR Code reader: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/qcode-decoder">https://www.npmjs.com/package/qcode-decoder</a></li>
  <li></li>
</ul>

<p>In fact, I built a QR code reader:<a href="https://qrsnapper.appspot.com/">https://qrsnapper.appspot.com/</a> 
— article about this soon.</p>

<h2 id="editors"><strong>Editors</strong></h2>

<p>I hate having to install native apps just to edit part of a file or image only 
once, and I don’t think I am alone. People like to open files and do things with 
them. Make a front end for it. </p>

<ul>
  <li>Hex Editor: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/hex">https://www.npmjs.com/package/hex</a></li>
  <li>Theme-color tool: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/color-scheme">https://www.npmjs.com/package/color-scheme</a></li>
  <li>JSON Editor:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/json-nice">https://www.npmjs.com/package/json-nice</a></li>
  <li>Quick PNG cropper: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/png-crop">https://www.npmjs.com/package/png-crop</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="players-and-readers"><strong>Players and Readers</strong></h2>

<p>There are a huge number of API’s that are clients for existing web services. For 
example any audio service normally has an API that lets you read play lists and 
gives you access to the audio.</p>

<ul>
  <li>SoundCloud player:<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/packages/soundcloud-audio">https://www.npmjs.com/packages/soundcloud-audio</a></li>
  <li>Reddit Reader: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/snoode">https://www.npmjs.com/package/snoode</a></li>
  <li>MixCloud player: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/mixcloud">https://www.npmjs.com/package/mixcloud</a></li>
  <li>ePub Reader / Summary: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/epub">https://www.npmjs.com/package/epub</a></li>
  <li>Tumblr client: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/tumblr">https://www.npmjs.com/package/tumblr</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="markdown-tools"><strong>Markdown tools</strong></h2>

<p>Creating content on the web is a pain in the bum sometimes, Markdown at least 
can help make the authorship easier.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Markdown to HTML: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/packages/markdown">https://www.npmjs.com/packages/markdown</a></li>
  <li>HTML to Markdown: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/to-markdown">https://www.npmjs.com/package/to-markdown</a></li>
  <li>Quick outline generator: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/markdown-outline">https://www.npmjs.com/package/markdown-outline</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The future of communications apps is on the web]]></title>
    <link href="/browsers/mobile/webapps/communications/serviceworker/2015/01/18/communications-apps-on-the-web.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-18T17:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/browsers/mobile/webapps/communications/serviceworker/2015/01/18/communications-apps-on-the-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>SMS is dying. WhatsApp, Line, WeChat, SnapChat and many others are making it 
easier to talk to friends, families and groups. A common feature across these 
apps is: They are all on native platforms and are on the web only to drive users 
to their native app install pages.</p>

<p><img src="/images/wechat.jpg" alt="WeChat &quot;web interface&quot;" /></p>

<p>I have spoken to a lot of developers about why their apps are only on native 
platforms, and to users about the <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/consumersurveys/view?survey=brtdoucbr2hje&amp;question=2&amp;dataGen=87&amp;tb=rt">features that 
they</a> need and it comes to several key areas: Installability for permanence, 
engagement via push notifications, ability to bootstrap the social graph via
the phone’s contacts and “it’s where the users are”.  The web for a lot of developers is just a tool to drive users to your installation  page in the store. </p>

<p>But what if you didn’t have to convert your user into an installed user, your 
user’s are already a real user the minute they land on your page?</p>

<p>2015 is the first year where the web stops being just a funnel to an app install 
page. 2015 is the year where the web is an accelerant of growth.</p>

<p>The web in 2015 will offer developers and users two huge benefits:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Increased methods for engagement </strong> — at the heart of it, the technology is 
in the browser today and the near future that means we can offer the same 
features as a native experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Low friction for user acquisition</strong> — given a link, a new user could be 
using the app within seconds, instead of having to go to a market, wait for 
the download, and then for the app install to happen.</li>
</ul>

<p>There are a number of features that users expect an app to be able to perform 
for it to be useful:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Presence</strong> — a user must have the confidence that a web based 
communications app lives on your device. If the user wants, it shouldn’t just 
be a link the user has to open in the browser to start using. It should launch 
like all apps on your device: from the home screen.</li>
  <li><strong>Persistence</strong> — a user must have the confidence that a web based 
communications apps will be available to work wherever they are. If there is 
no internet connection, it must still load and present all previous 
communication and message creation tools.</li>
  <li><strong>Integration</strong> — a user must have the confidence that they will never miss 
anything. Their friend sends them a message, it should notify them of the 
status via notification exactly as they expect irrespective of if the browser 
window is open or closed.</li>
  <li><strong>Media Access</strong> — a user expects to be able to communicate in mediums 
other than plain text, they should be able to access the camera, the photo 
gallery and audio.</li>
</ul>

<p>The question is: the web is ephemeral with pages being born when a URL is opened 
and dying when the user closes the browser and has little to no access to the 
hardware, how can you get the <strong>Presence, Persistence, Integration, **Media 
Access</strong> (It’s been noticed that an acronym for this is A PIMP) required to 
build a next generation communications app? </p>

<p>Answer: Service Worker and the recent additions to the web platform.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Presence</strong> — Web App Manifest gives you the entry point into your web app 
and defines how it appears when installed on the system and registration of a 
Service Worker (even a Service Worker that does nothing) means that your web app 
can live in the background asleep and only to be woken when the device needs it 
to be.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Persistence</strong> — A Service Worker registration can control and manage every 
request that comes through the web app, this gives an unprecedented level of 
control, we can store the UI and logic permanently and cache the data in the app 
locally, sync back up from the server if required.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Integration</strong> — The most interesting area. <em>You will</em>, via Service Worker, be 
able to manage push messaging to your app. Think of this as telecoms signaling. 
Your web app can be asleep before being woken up by the devices push messaging 
service to process the data in the payload. From here you could choose to 
synchronise data in the background so it is fresh and available to the user when 
they next open the app, or trigger a notification to alert the user that they 
need to take action.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Media Access</strong> — WebRTC has brought us access to the users microphone and 
camera (with permission) and also a real-time bridge directly to the people we 
want to talk to.  Services like FaceTime and Skype are entirely possible in the 
browser.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>At the core, we have fixed many of the big issues. Today you can go and build 
WhatSnapChap entirely on the web and it can compete with the majority of 
communications apps today but there are some areas that still need to be 
improved:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Contacts Access</strong> — Many communications apps have access to your address 
book either so you can send a link to them directly via SMS or email, or so 
that function can be delegated to the service and used to find other users on 
their service that you know.</li>
  <li><strong>Ubiquity</strong> — Your site will be accessible by anyone who can hit the URL, you 
have to be happy with that fact that not everyone will be able to use every 
feature of your app, but they should still be able to access it.  Maybe you 
don’t have push notifications for Gingerbread users on Android browser, but 
they should still be able to read messages that were synced from a server.<br />
It’s a choice you will have to make.</li>
  <li><strong>Payments</strong> — Web apps aren’t yet built into the devices payments 
platforms so as a developer you have to integrate many third party payments 
systems, this can present a burden to the developer but also can confuse the 
user, however when considering the American audience that I asked, Payments 
weren’t a large feature.</li>
</ul>

<p>The web that we had yesterday was never capable of even trying to take on the 
capabilities of a native application.  In 2015 the technology is there. Service Worker
opens up a new range of experiences and combined with the basic properties of the web
provides a vastly smoother user on-boarding experience. </p>

<p>Can we build a SnapChat? 
<strong>Yes, absolutely.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do people want from a news experience?]]></title>
    <link href="/browsers/mobile/news/2014/12/08/what-news-readers-want.html"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T17:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/browsers/mobile/news/2014/12/08/what-news-readers-want</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One thing that I am working on at the moment is breaking up each of the verticals
that define an app (News, Retail, Games, Travel, Media etc) and working out
what use-cases they need and how web technology can solve them.  </p>

<p>An area that I am really interested in is News apps, many organisations report that the only
place that they are seeing growth in engagment and revenue is on Mobile,
specifically Mobile Apps.</p>

<p>In Developer Relations we often think of what cool demo can we build with a
new API.  This time I have decided that rather than start with what I think a
developer wants (i.e, shiney demo), I would instead start by asking users what
they want from a “News experience” and then tailor our developer message
accordingly.</p>

<p>I posit that users want (in order of priority):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Notifications of important news as it happens</li>
  <li>An icon on the launcher so it can be loaded like an app</li>
  <li>News available to them offline (i.e, when they are in the tube)</li>
  <li>A fast site</li>
</ul>

<p>My own intuition of an industry I am not too heavily involved in probably can’t
be trusted as much as I think it can, so I sent out a terrbily worded Tweet.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>What to Native News paper apps do that you can&#39;t do on the web?</p>&mdash; Paul Kinlan (@Paul_Kinlan) <a href="https://twitter.com/Paul_Kinlan/status/539737443055185921">December 2, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>This got a number of interesting replies:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/Paul_Kinlan">@paul_kinlan</a> Offline caching &amp; UX speed, mostly. Compare <a href="http://t.co/9W28fXbyvB">http://t.co/9W28fXbyvB</a> with WSJ iPad app. And, v important, one-tap iTunes payment</p>&mdash; Benedict Evans (@BenedictEvans) <a href="https://twitter.com/BenedictEvans/status/540027507488346112">December 3, 2014</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>In the entire thread it boiled down to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Performance, apps are percieved to be faster and smoother</li>
  <li>Access to content offline</li>
  <li>Content synced and available</li>
  <li>Notifications of new content</li>
  <li>Efficient payments</li>
  <li>and icon in the launcher.</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s not that I didn’t believe this (it is broadly what I have in our 2015
plans) but I wanted to try and validate the results. I decided to try
<a href="http://www.google.com/insights/consumersurveys/">Google Consumer Surveys</a>
(other good survey tools might exist but I think it is rather awesome), it seemed
like an awesome tool to do the analysis and had a decent sized user base.</p>

<p>My goal was to find out: of the people who prefer to read their news in an App,
what do they prefer about it? The sample was constrained to US users of an
Android Smartphone, the prime audience of App using News consumers if reports
are accurate.</p>

<p>The first question: How do you prefer to consume the news? Is a filter and offers 
“In an app”, on the “web” or “Other” (Other is a mandatory escape hatch).  If the user
selected “in an app” they were taken to a 2nd set of questions to learn more
about what they value in a News App experience.</p>

<p>The second question was: What features do you want from a news experience?  This was a multi-choice question
so you had the option of select as many features as you wanted from the list:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Notifications for new content</li>
  <li>News automatically available in the morning</li>
  <li>News available offline</li>
  <li>An icon on the homescreen</li>
  <li>Smooth navigation</li>
</ul>

<p>The results were interesting. Of the people surveyed, <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/consumersurveys/view?survey=xqnkc3hqtrucy&amp;question=1">most preferred to
consume the news on the web</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/news-web-vs-app.png" alt="Web vs Native" /></p>

<p>It might be worth following up this survey in a couple of months or a year to
see what the trajectory is.  Maybe that 30% of people who prefer an app for
reading the news is up from 5% last year. Who knows?</p>

<p>Whilst this was an interesting aside the most important thing is to understand
what in the App world people really like.</p>

<p>The results of the features that people want from a News reading experience
did suprise me.</p>

<p><img src="/images/news-app-features.png" alt="App features" /></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/consumersurveys/view?survey=xqnkc3hqtrucy&amp;question=2">vast majority of App users preferred speed and smoothness</a> in
their reading experience and they want the news available in the morning.</p>

<p>Why is this a suprise? </p>

<p>Performance is a given.  My suprise was that if you make it fast and make the content 
available in the morning you would make 90% of users happy.  </p>

<p>If you look at the what the Chrome team and standards bodies are building - the Push API in particular - having a News Web experience integrate the API will only increment the user satisfaction a small amount.</p>

<p>This is not what my intuition suggested.  Are we working on the wrong priorities?</p>

<p>So what now?  It is clear that we need to do more research when understanding
how we tell developers to integrate our platform features.  With regards to
News I do want to tailor our developer messaging to a number of important areas
with News being one of them, I just need to work out how to do it. Some thoughts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It is clear that we need to drive it home to developers that it is possible
to build fast and smooth experiences on the web and show them how to do it.</li>
  <li>Show developers how to build experiences that install, work offline and sync
when users want them to.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>TL;DR</em> We need to show developers how to build great apps on the web in the contexts they expect.</p>

<p>All the results are available for <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/consumersurveys/view?survey=xqnkc3hqtrucy&amp;question=1">everyone to read</a>. </p>

<p>I would love your feedback.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living with Web Apps]]></title>
    <link href="/browsers/mobile/webapps/2014/08/20/living-with-web-apps.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T17:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>/browsers/mobile/webapps/2014/08/20/living-with-web-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a Developer Advocate for Google Chrome and the Web it is my job to build a 
picture of how the Web works and educate developer on how to build for it, but 
also craft a vision for how developers should build for the future starting 
today.</p>

<p>I am a firm believer that we should be building and deploying apps on the web 
powered by a runtime that is the browser. The web offers a medium that is 
frictionless for user to engage with. A user can just visit your URL… you get 
it, but can we go day to day using just the web on mobile?</p>

<p>I decided to spend a day using only the web for all the tasks that people use 
their mobile phone for. No exceptions. Everything interaction that I do <strong>must</strong> 
be via the web.</p>

<p><strong>TL;DR — the 10 deadly sins of a mobile web app </strong>— You can get stuff done, but 
there are a lot of rough edges that stop you from doing the things that you need 
to. Some of the issues are not anything the developer can do just yet, it is the 
platform that they are fighting against. Luckily, I know what is coming on the 
platform so I am very optimistic that the feature gap will be reduced for Apps 
on the web. </p>

<p>Ultimately this experiment has shaped the way that I want us (Chrome Developer 
Relations) to get developers building for the web today and tomorrow. </p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>It’s not mobile</strong>: Some of the newer services have good mobile web 
experiences but there are huge areas where web developers still think desktop 
first or desktop only.</li>
  <li><strong>Lack of focus</strong>: It sometimes feels like Web Apps are often considered as 
documents with functionality in.  There is some functionality, then a 
document thanking everyone who helped.  Play 2048 as an example.</li>
  <li><strong>Discovery is a massive issue</strong>: Finding great web apps is incredibly hard 
and I have little confidence that they work well on mobile even when I see a 
top link in Google.</li>
  <li><strong>Everything is ephemeral</strong>: This is great for a lot of experiences; I pick 
up a site use it once and I am done. There are a huge number of apps — all 
communications apps for example — where I need the app to live in the 
background to be able to deliver notifications but they can’t.</li>
  <li><strong>It’s not interconnected</strong>: Everything appears to operate in a silo or 
everything is tightly coupled to a service. I don’t use dropbox, I use drive, 
now I can’t use your service to save my stuff.  I light-weight mechanism for 
interconnecting apps would really help. </li>
  <li><strong>Everything is monolithic</strong>: I found it incredibly hard to find small 
self-contained mobile apps that just solved my problem without being a 
service that I had to sign-up for and adopt. </li>
  <li><strong>Everything needs credential but nothing keeps credentials</strong>: I have to 
either create an account or re-sign in to everything all the time. I can’t 
tell if it is a hangover from the shared desktop era that means web apps must 
be logged out after use. This is not something I experience in many mobile 
apps. I log in once.</li>
  <li><strong>It’s slow and ugly out there</strong>: There is a serious lack of polish in many 
experiences; I had very little confidence that the apps would offer what I 
wanted when I found them and when I used them there were a lot of jarring 
animations and transitions.</li>
  <li><strong>White screens rule the day</strong>: Offline was not a big issue for me, however 
white pages in transitions really annoyed me; I found myself just waiting for 
the screen to load and getting frustrated when my entire UI was rebuilt.</li>
  <li><strong>The platform has a lot of features, just not the right ones</strong>: This is a 
meta-point, but if feels like the API space on the web does not yet cater for 
even the basic type of interaction with my device that I need; Notifications 
and Push Messaging were greatly missed.</li>
</ol>

<p>There are about apps that I want to build now. I am sorely tempted to start a 
movement getting people to build <strong>good</strong> utility apps.</p>

<h2 id="journal-the-experiment">Journal: The Experiment</h2>

<p><strong>11:30 PM — The night before the experiment</strong><br />
If I had been smart marketing type person I would have run this experiment on 
Wednesday, but alas I am a simple man with simple ideas.</p>

<p>The night before “Web App Thursday” — an evening I like to now call Shrove 
Wednesday, a day of native app gluttony —  I set up my home screen to launch the 
apps that I use regularly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/homescreen.jpg" alt="My homescreen" /></p>

<p>The first thing that I noticed is the inconsistent usage of launcher icons 
across all service. Services that you would expect to have good “app” icons just 
don’t (notably all by the company that I work for — bugs have been raised) many 
services that I relegated to my 2nd screen didn’t even have favicons.</p>

<p>It totally slipped my mind that I needed to replace the camera, dialer and SMS. 
Later when I realized to further compound my issues I had an existential crisis 
about the browser being a native app, but I chose to ignore that and keep this 
simple.</p>

<p>With my “workflow” set up I went to bed, watched some QI from the Netflix App 
that was integrated with my Chrome Cast. Bliss…</p>

<hr />
<p><strong>5:53 AM — Youngest son sits on my head to wake me up</strong><br />
Seriously. He sits on my head.<br />
Groggily I roughly remember something about only using the web today before I 
fall back asleep.</p>

<p><strong>6:00 AM — Web App Thursday. BZZZZ. BZZZZ. BZZZZ</strong></p>

<p>Alarm wakes me up. Trundle across to my phone to snooze the damn thing and start 
to feel optimistic about my day using only the web on my phone. Now I am not the 
sharpest fork on the shelf, but as I am walking to the loo (phone in hand) I 
realize that I have already failed. Alarm clock is a Native App.</p>

<p>Whilst I deal with the fact that I am a failure I notice that it is impossible 
to find web based alarm clock apps that work on mobile which kind of makes 
sense; There is no API yet that will let you background an app and get it to 
wake up at a specific time. However the more frustrating this is that even 
countdown timers are hard to find and when you do find them in search they are 
all aimed at desktop.</p>

<p>Some people have managed to get around the API issues by using Flash but:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Flash is not an option on mobile</li>
  <li>You have to have the page always open</li>
  <li>They are ugly</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>6:15 AM — …</strong><br />
<strong>6:25 AM — The dead leg walk downstairs</strong><br />
Enthused that the rest of my day was likely to be gassing on Twitter or checking 
emails I reset my experiment status. </p>

<p>At this point I also thought I need a shift in narrative; logging everything by 
time is a pain (I can’t find a good app for it). Not only is it hard to write 
like this, but it also really hard to find an app that keeps a time ordered log 
of what happened and when.</p>

<p>It is a lot easier to write based on the tasks that I needed to complete during 
the day.</p>

<h2 id="use-cases">Use cases</h2>

<p>I took copious notes during the day of things that worked well and areas that 
were frustrating. I have broken the results down into use cases that were 
important to me.</p>

<h3 id="being-prompted-at-certain-times">Being prompted at certain times</h3>

<p>I found a couple of Countdown timers but that is about it. Alarms are pretty 
much standard on mobile devices so there is a question about the need to do this 
on the web.  I only wanted to do two things: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Set a quick alarm based on a fixed time</li>
  <li>Quickly set a countdown for X minutes</li>
</ul>

<p>The latter we can do, but I can’t find good apps.  The former can’t be done when 
the browser is backgrounded.</p>

<h3 id="note-taking">Note taking</h3>

<p>I did a quick search for a note taking apps on the web and there were a few but 
interestingly my overriding need was something that I could just quickly start 
taking notes in.  I didn’t want to sign up for services or cloud integration, I 
just wanted to start taking notes. </p>

<p>I use Google Keep at work and have never tried it on the web on mobile but I 
thought I should give it a go I couldn’t really find anything better quickly.</p>

<p>To my surprise Google Keep works quite well on the mobile web. With a couple of 
exceptions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>It can’t run full screen like a native app, it doesn’t even have a launcher 
icon.</li>
  <li>I can’t share something to it (like a link) to create a note</li>
  <li>The navigation bar Janks.</li>
  <li>Offline… er, no.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="communicating-with-people">Communicating with People</h3>

<p>A lot of my time on my phone is spent communicating with people. Email, Twitter, 
G+ and SMS are my main medium, voice less so. </p>

<p>During the day Email (gmail in particular) worked well although it is out-dated 
in terms of modern web based UI’s with some quirks in the typing experience and 
that focus highlighter is annoying.</p>

<p>Twitter also worked pretty well, I could post, DM and search. It launches 
fullscreen, it feels like an app (heck I can even load it offline) and it loads 
very quickly and provided 90% of what I needed. The web experience on mobile is 
still last years site, it doesn’t look like any of the native mobile 
experiences.</p>

<p>Twitter and Email were the first apps that I noticed that the “ephemeral” nature 
of the web significantly hindered my ability to communicate with friends and 
family. Earlier in the day I had turned off system notifications and none of 
these experiences have the ability to live in the background and notify me when 
an interesting interaction occurs. After about 4 hours of a quiet morning I 
ended up turning them back on so at least I knew when I should check for 
updates.</p>

<p>The web is not fully integrated in to the native communication stack. There are 
no dialers. There are no Web based SMS apps and whilst you can just about create 
an SMS from the web, you can’t send or read them directly via a web app.  I have 
an open question about </p>

<h3 id="reading-news-and-content">Reading News and Content</h3>

<p>Hacker News and Reddit are terrible on mobile. Seriously, I don’t get why they 
don’t even try. I am being hard on Reddit because they have at least<a href="http://reddit.com/.compact"> 
</a><a href="http://reddit.com/.compact">.compact</a> but they 
steer everyone away into apps.</p>

<p>I am an extensive user of Google Play Newsstand app on Android, it does a decent 
job of getting me the content I want to read both Purchased and also “web 
available”. I had no idea what to expect checking this site on the mobile web 
and to my surprise I can read my subscription content but it is a bare bones 
experience, there is no ‘text’ mode (it is only images) and the gestures don’t 
work the same.  I was disappointed to find that the “web article” reading mode 
is not supported at all.</p>

<p>Many news sites worked great (even if they did m.* redirects).  None of them 
felt like “app experiences” and this is interesting because many news sites are 
reporting more engagement and reading inside apps.</p>

<h3 id="watching-video-and-listening-to-audio">Watching Video and Listening to Audio</h3>

<p>I watch a lot of video and listen to podcasts quite frequently and I wasn’t 
expecting a huge amount in terms of mobile web experience.</p>

<p>I made sure that I used the mobile web version of YouTube.  It is a pretty good 
experience although it lacks the UX smoothness of the native app.  I did find 
that very frequently the browser wouldn’t render any of the visible content (but 
would play the video) and I wasn’t able to isolate the exact circumstances.</p>

<p>I was very pleased to find that Google Play Movies works even with protected 
content.  There were a couple of small scrolling issue left to right and the 
media player appears to be YouTube. Whilst the entire UI is very clunky and slow 
it works.</p>

<p>For podcasts Player.fm is my client of choice and it works pretty well on 
mobile. The audio plays even when I background the application, however there 
are no controls to let you play or pause the sound or even get back to the site 
easily once you have backgrounded Chrome.</p>

<h3 id="camera">Camera</h3>

<p>My two sons were doing something cute and I needed to take a photo quickly. As 
far as I can tell there are no “Camera apps” on the web for mobile, ones I found 
were optimized for desktop, used Flash and didn’t save directly to my phones 
gallery.</p>

<p>Once I had taken the photos, I wanted to quickly crop the images and apply some 
filters to share them out. Yup. You guessed it. I couldn’t find any apps that do 
this.  </p>

<p>This is one of the areas where I completely bailed on the web and it frustrated 
me.  I can’t retrieve and modify the photo’s on my device in a seamless manner.</p>

<p>I also took some time to think about how a developer might build the camera 
experience and naturally my first thought was to use “getUserMedia” API. If you 
look further into this API then it doesn’t offer any <a href="https://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/detail?id=343894">advanced features</a> that you expect in a <em>good</em> camera app: focus, flash, zoom etc. It is clear that this API 
has been designed for use in P2P applications and not as a dedicated camera 
experience.</p>

<h3 id="gaming">Gaming</h3>

<p>I found <strong>one</strong> great game during the day that took up a good chunk of down 
time:<a href="http://buff.ly/1nLSjtT"> </a><a href="http://buff.ly/1nLSjtT">Game about Squares</a> is 
a brilliant, simple, mobile optimized game. Don’t get me wrong, 2048 is a great 
game and it works on the mobile web however it has a very document feel to it.<br />
I found that games suffered all the same problems of Apps:  I can’t find them, 
they feel like documents rather than apps and more often than not they are still 
desktop games.</p>

<h2 id="pervasive-issues-over-the-day">Pervasive Issues over the day</h2>

<h3 id="lack-of-confidence">Lack of Confidence</h3>

<p>I really had no confidence in many of the apps that I found. </p>

<ul>
  <li>Some experiences I wanted them to load instantly when launched, the white 
screen for loading felt like I was gambling at every moment.</li>
  <li>I got a white screen so frequently it got really frustrating when 
transitioning between pages that I couldn’t tell if it was Chrome or the App 
that is causing the problem or just the way we build apps.</li>
  <li>I had no idea that any of the apps would do what I wanted.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="white-screens-follow-me-around-everywhere">White screens follow me around everywhere</h3>

<p>In nearly every app and site I used I felt like the majority of my time was 
spent waiting for content to load. It was really frustrating, when I use native
apps I very rarely get this.  Whilst I see in natvie apps that there are placeholders
for the content to load I still get to see the entire app UI.</p>

<h3 id="jankstutter-is-pervasive">Jank/Stutter is pervasive</h3>

<p>Watching UI elements move on the screen was toe-curling.   Navigation trays 
seemed to be a big offender during the day.  I would often click on the tray 
icon, wait, and then see a 4fps animation.</p>

<p>That being said, there are some sites that work really well.  The twitter app 
and g+ app both have really great scrolling on my phone.</p>

<h3 id="notifications">Notifications</h3>

<p>I knew going in to this that we don’t have background push messaging and 
notifications, but it is not until you don’t have them do you realise it is one 
of the primary ways that you engage with your applications on your device.</p>

<h3 id="form-filling">Form filling</h3>

<p>I tried to book my hotel that I stay in during the week on mobile.  I had to 
bail and go to desktop, it was terrible.  The site wasn’t optimised for mobile, 
but at the same time I was just cautious anytime that I had to enter text.</p>

<h3 id="sharing-content">Sharing Content</h3>

<p>There are lots of things that I create on my phone every day and I can’t share 
them with any web services.  When I took a picture of the kids I was forced to 
take the photo with an app and share it via an app.  Likewise when I wanted to 
share something from the browser I couldn’t share it to any other web 
experience, I kept having to share it to a native app.</p>

<p>Add to this Chrome is pretty poor at sharing content natively.  You can’t long press on 
images or links and share them out (these were the only things I needed to share 
in the day).</p>

<h3 id="lack-of-basic-device-interaction">Lack of basic device interaction</h3>

<p>I get that we have access to geo-location and device orientation, but I also 
found that I wanted to do simple things such as selecting and saving images to 
and from my photo gallery in a near seamless fashion and I couldn’t do it.  If I 
was playing audio on a page I would have loved to be able to control that from 
the lock screen and I couldn’t do it, I had to go tab hunting.  I also really 
wanted to have a camera app that I could trust and do basic actions on (focus 
and flash) and I couldn’t do it.</p>

<h3 id="discovery">Discovery</h3>

<p>It is hard to find apps.  It is even hard to find good apps that work well.  It 
felt impossible to find good apps that work well and have a nice user 
experience.  I had to rely on my social network to find apps.  Search sometimes 
did find web apps for some common use-cases, but it doesn’t rank quality.  Both 
the Chrome Web Store and Firefox marketplace are not great, CWS is impossible to 
navigate on mobile, FF is a lot better.  Neither let you launch a hosted web app 
directly from an app result.  </p>

<p>This was so frustrating, the only places that I  know has apps and I can’t do anything 
with it.</p>

<h3 id="lack-of-small-utilities">Lack of small utilities</h3>

<p>Most of the time I wanted some small apps to help me complete a task, these 
might exist, but even after deep searches for them the utilities are primarily 
desktop only, horrible user experiences, large services that need registration 
or they don’t exist.  There are about 20 simple core utility apps that we should 
build on the web and market them as “the primary” web experiences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[This is the web platform]]></title>
    <link href="/browsers/mobile/2014/02/24/this-is-the-web-platform.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T17:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/browsers/mobile/2014/02/24/this-is-the-web-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Feature</th>
      <th>On Desktop</th>
      <th>On Mobile</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>PNG alpha transparency</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>querySelector/querySelectorAll</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>getElementsByClassName</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Multiple backgrounds</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Background-image options</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Table display</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Generated content</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS 2.1 selectors</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 selectors</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Text-shadow</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Colors</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Box-sizing</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Media Queries</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Multiple column layout</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Canvas (basic support)</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cross-document messaging</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Data URIs</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>XHTML served as application/xhtml+xml</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Opacity</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>JSON parsing</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Text-overflow</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Overflow-wrap</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS min/max-width/height</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS inline-block</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>dataset &amp; data-* attributes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Counters</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>getComputedStyle</td>
      <td> </td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>contentEditable</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Drag and Drop</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Pretty damning.</p>

<p>At “100%” coverage of features that are in all browsers split by Mobile and Desktop then this is all we have to play with.</p>

<p>Ok, this is actually misleading.  If you are <a href="http://ondesktop.iwanttouse.com/#cors">willing to miss out on 1% extra reach for your desktop</a> audience then you can get similar feature parity with mobile.  But still the feature support that is ubiquitous across the web is actually pretty small especially if you are supporting IE8.</p>

<h2 id="how-do-i-know-what-the-web-platform-is">How do I know what the web platform is?</h2>

<p>Last year I built <a href="http://iwanttouse.com">iwanttouse.com</a> to make it easier for you to determine the cost on your userbase supporting certain features will have.  <em>If I support X, I can only reach Y% of the web’s users</em></p>

<p>The project is pretty simple.  It is a projection of the data on <a href="http://caniuse.com">CanIUse.com</a>. For a given “feature” it looks for the earliest version on a platform that it was supported on and sums the “usage”.  </p>

<p>I split the feature set by <a href="http://onmobile.iwanttouse.com">Mobile</a> and <a href="http://ondesktop.iwanttouse.com">Desktop</a> and it gives you some pretty interesting nuggets of data.</p>

<p>Two things that fell out of this: </p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Features for Free</strong>.  If I choose <a href="http://www.iwanttouse.com/#audio-api">Web Audio</a> (43% on mobile) I can also safely use other features such as <a href="http://www.iwanttouse.com/#eventsource">Server-sent DOM Events</a> because all browsers that support the former support the latter. (Note: the inverse relationship is not always true)</li>
  <li><strong>Ubiquitous Platform features</strong>.  As above but platform features that we can rely on being present in all browsers with any significant share.</li>
</ul>

<p>I want to focus on <strong>Ubiquitous Platform features</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="how-do-we-improve-the-web-platform">How do we improve the web platform?</h2>

<p>As a web developer today I face a couple of problems: Legacy browsers that aren’t updated and inconsistent implementation across browsers.  </p>

<p>The web feels like a pirate ship, everyone is hacking and slashing in different directions and we are lucky enough that the ship goes forwards.  Slowly.  How do we become a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Ainslie">Ben Ainslie</a> America’s Cup winning yacht?… (Ack, I can’t believe I said that).  Point is, how can we improve the modern mobile web consistently if there are multiple large players in the eco-system?</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wait it out and let the Browser vendors do their thing.  This will change over time as people move off the platforms that have stopped progressing as their devices are renewed.</li>
  <li>Ignore the old browsers and the users that use them and go for it.</li>
  <li>Push for consistency across the platform.</li>
</ol>

<p>My preference is for 2 and 3.  But actually 1 is what we <em>really</em> <strong>really</strong> need to solve.</p>

<p>I like to solve level 1 problems — problems with a technical solution — they’re the things I can fix.  I can meet developers and work with them on their sites to measurably make the web better one large site at a time, but it is all small scale…</p>

<p>I decided to take a peek at the features that are supported across the latest mobile browsers and the reach that will have:  <strong><a href="http://onmobile.iwanttouse.com/#geolocation,flexbox">44%</a></strong>.  We can’t honestly say to a business that you should build experiences for 44% of your potential user base (well, it depends who you want to sell or attract - your demographics might be highly skewed - i.e.. Government legislation, Business demands.)</p>

<p>If you look at the  head of the mobile web (44%) there is a compelling feature set.  You can build some amazing applications with it.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Feature</th>
      <th>Android Browser 4.4</th>
      <th>iOS Safari 7.0</th>
      <th>Chrome for Android 32.0</th>
      <th>IE Mobile 10.0</th>
      <th>Opera Mobile 16.0</th>
      <th>Firefox for Android 26.0</th>
      <th>Blackberry Browser 10.0</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>XHTML served as application/xhtml+xml</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>XMLHttpRequest 2</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WOFF - Web Open Font Format</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Web Workers</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Web Sockets</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Video element</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ECMAScript 5 Strict Mode</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Typed Arrays</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Transforms</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Text-overflow</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG in HTML img element</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Inline SVG in HTML5</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG filters</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG in CSS backgrounds</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG (basic support)</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>defer attribute for external scripts</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>async attribute for external scripts</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>requestAnimationFrame</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>rem (root em) units</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>querySelector/querySelectorAll</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>PNG alpha transparency</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Page Visibility</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS outline</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Offline web applications</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Web Storage - name/value pairs</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Multiple backgrounds</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS min/max-width/height</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>matchMedia</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>JSON parsing</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Range input type</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>input placeholder attribute</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS inline-block</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>sandbox attribute for iframes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>New semantic elements</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session history management</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Hashchange event</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>getElementsByClassName</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>getComputedStyle</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Geolocation</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>@font-face Web fonts</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>FileReader API</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Colors</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Transitions</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Text-shadow</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Table display</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 selectors</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS 2.1 selectors</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Repeating Gradients</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Opacity</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Media Queries</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Gradients</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Generated content</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Counters</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Box-shadow</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Animation</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>contenteditable attribute (basic support)</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>classList (DOMTokenList )</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Text API for Canvas</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Canvas (basic support)</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>calc() as CSS unit value</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Border-radius (rounded corners)</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Background-image options</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Audio element</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cross-document messaging</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 3D Transforms</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>MPEG-4/H.264 video format</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Data URIs</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>dataset &amp; data-* attributes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS position:fixed</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Content Security Policy</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Blob constructing</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Overflow-wrap</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Progress &amp; Meter</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Flexible Box Layout Module</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>But like I said. <em>44%</em>.  It’s a big head but not a feasible platform for the vast majority of companies.  I produced the following breakdown of features that we should get Chrome and other vendors to fix feature support at a tactical level to make for a more consistent web and make developers lives easier.  The problem is we are only fixing it for <em>44%</em> of the web’s users.  <em>Documented below for consistency</em></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Feature</th>
      <th>Android Browser 4.4</th>
      <th>iOS Safari 7.0</th>
      <th>Chrome for Android 32.0</th>
      <th>IE Mobile 10.0</th>
      <th>Opera Mobile 16.0</th>
      <th>Firefox for Android 26.0</th>
      <th>Blackberry Browser 10.0</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>TTF/OTF - TrueType and OpenType font support</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Unknown</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Touch events</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Navigation Timing API</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mutation Observer</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Intrinsic &amp; Extrinsic Sizing</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Font feature settings</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>File API</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Server-sent DOM events</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 tab-size</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Channel messaging</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Border images</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Blob URLs</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Viewport units: vw, vh, vmin, vmax</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG SMIL animation</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>IndexedDB</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 word-break</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG fonts</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Download attribute</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Details &amp; Summary elements</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Filter Effects</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Multiple column layout</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Date/time input types</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HTML5 form features</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Form validation</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 Box-sizing</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WAI-ARIA Accessibility features</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG effects for HTML</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>matches() DOM method</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HTML templates</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Strict Transport Security</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Unknown</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>getUserMedia/Stream API</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Color input type</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Feature Queries</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Clipboard API</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Canvas blend modes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ruby annotation</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Number input type</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>DeviceOrientation events</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WebGL - 3D Canvas graphics</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Web Notifications</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Full Screen API</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WebP image format</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SVG fragment identifiers</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shadow DOM</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WebRTC Peer-to-peer connections</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>MathML</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Filesystem &amp; FileWriter API</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Masks</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Web Audio API</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>WebM video format</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Datalist element</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Hyphenation</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Regions</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Promises</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Scoped CSS</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shared Web Workers</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Opus</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ogg/Theora video format</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>JPEG XR image format</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Drag and Drop</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS resize property</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Grid Layout</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pointer events</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS3 object-fit/object-position</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Toolbar/context menu</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CSS Variables</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Blending of CSS image</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Getting these features implemented would be cool but there is no additional reach at all. More users will not be affected by these new features.  We didn’t increase the size of the user base.  Yes we might get an amazing WebGL based WebComponents app that people use  but will they upgrade their browser or phone to be able to use it?  Probably not.</p>

<h2 id="so-what-do-we-do">So what do we do?</h2>

<p>How do we move the web platform forward in a meaningful way?  </p>

<p>It is hard.</p>

<p>Do we want to get back to a world where this is a thing?</p>

<p><img src="/images/ienetscape.jpg" alt="best viewed in" /></p>

<p>Maybe.???</p>

<p>At a minimum we should:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.iwanttouse.com/#css-boxshadow">Build for the 90%</a> and get your partners and customers to see at a minimum the experience that you can build with a huge amount of reach.</li>
  <li><a href="http://caniuse.com">Understand the choices</a> you make and the <a href="http://iwanttouse.com">impact they have</a>. Push your customers and partners to use progressive enchancement.  Don’t exclude a huge number of users for a single feature.</li>
  <li>Push for consistency over new platform features across all browser vendors.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=.%40Paul_Kinlan+you+are+wrong+about+the+web+because...">Tell me I am wrong</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

