<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: adb, | ]]></title>
  <link href="/categories/adb-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-11T13:55:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bootstraping your own mobile web testing lab for Android Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="/chrome,/mobile,/adb,/android/2013/02/04/bootstraping-your-own-mobile-device-lab-part-1.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T11:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/chrome,/mobile,/adb,/android/2013/02/04/bootstraping-your-own-mobile-device-lab-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do you do if you want to quickly test your sites on mutliple versions of Android at the same time?</p>

<p>There are couple of solutions, such as <a href="http://html.adobe.com/edge/inspect/">Adobe Edge Inspect</a>, but what if you want to create and manage your own in your own workflow?  I haven’t seen single solution yet.</p>

<p>Here is a simple shell script that I created that starts to get you on your way to your own testing lab.  It connects to every single Android device that is attached to your machine by using <code>adb</code> (Android Debugging tool).</p>

<p>The process is as follows (and please suggest better ways):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Kill any existing adb servers</li>
  <li>Get a list of attached devices</li>
  <li>For each device set up port forwarding (required for <a href="https://developers.google.com/chrome-developer-tools/docs/remote-debugging">Chrome Dev tools</a>)</li>
  <li>Fire Android intent to open the browser (with a url if one is on the command line)</li>
</ul>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/4706201.js"></script>

<p>It’s not a complete solution, but it is a nice way to start.  My ultimate goal is to have a <a href="http://www.xda-developers.com/android/adb-fully-working-on-raspberry-pi/">Raspberry PI</a> hosting adb and all the devices that I can attach to it with an attached proxy that will route all my devtools requests to the correct device.</p>

<p>How do you test across mutliple devices?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

