<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hackathon | ]]></title>
  <link href="/categories/hackathon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-11T13:55:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hackathons don't win you customers]]></title>
    <link href="/hackathon/2013/08/20/hackathons-dont-win-you-customers.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T22:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>/hackathon/2013/08/20/hackathons-dont-win-you-customers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oddly I rarely talk about Developer Relations, but I feel like changing that today.</p>

<p>I feel really uncomfortable when I hear people suggest Hackathons are a part of building a sustainable, scalable developer ecosystem.  </p>

<p><strong>They are not.</strong></p>

<p>I have run hackathons.  Some better than others.  I have learnt a lot about them.</p>

<p>Businesses and Platform creators:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you are thinking of running a hackathon to win potential new customers <strong>you are doing it wrong</strong>.</li>
  <li>If you are wanting someone to start a business by using your platform at your hackathon <strong>you are doing it wrong</strong>.</li>
  <li>If you are running hackathons to raise brand awareness <strong>you are doing it wrong</strong>.</li>
  <li>If you are offering winners $SOMERANDOMLARGENUMBER <strong>you are doing it wrong</strong>.</li>
  <li>If your product team (PMs through to Eng) are not at the hackathon <strong>you are doing it wrong</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Hackathons can be a thing of beauty, they can produce completely unexpected demos, but that is not your goal. You should be using it as a learning exercise for <strong>you</strong>, <strong>your team</strong> and <strong>fixing your product</strong>.  It is the developer version of a beta test, not a marketing tool.</p>

<p>Learn from the developers using your platform.  Ask yourselves the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Do your demos work? are developers using the demos to build on top of them?</li>
  <li>Does your documentation work? can developers start by diving into the docs and following the guides step by step?</li>
  <li>Does your platform work?  Is your API intuitive?  Are developers getting stuck on certain parts?</li>
  <li>Is there value to your platform?  Is it possible for people to build sustainable integrations on your platform?</li>
</ul>

<p>You can answer all these questions at a Hackathon.  That is what you should be concentrating on.</p>

<p>One little point, rather than just rewarding teams who produce a lot, reward filing bugs and issues on all parts of your product, the apis, the documentation, the demos and the value as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

